Guide to the Women's Athletics Photograph Collection 1899-1958
Oregon State University Libraries, University Archives
Women's Athletics Photograph Collection
1899-1958
1921-1940
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center University Archives 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2165 Email: archives@oregonstate.edu Web: http://osulibrary.oregonstate.edu/archives
P 009
0.03 cubic foot, including 60 photographs 2 boxes, including 1 oversize box
The Women's Athletics Photograph Collection consists of images of teams, events, and individual athletes participating in a variety of sports and recreational activities at Oregon State, primarily during the 1920s and 1930s.
Historical Note:
Intramural and intercollegiate athletics as well as physical recreation activities have been offered for women at Oregon State since at least as early as the 1890s. During the early and middle decades of the 20th century, Oregon State had one of the largest women's athletics program in the northwest. Oregon State's first basketball team was the women's team, established in 1898 and preceding the first men's team by 3 years. Several women basketball players were selected to receive the college emblem in the early 1900s by the Athletic Union.
The Women's Athletics Photograph Collection consists of images of teams, events, and individual athletes participating in a variety of sports and recreational activities at Oregon State, primarily during the 1920s and 1930s. The collection includes images of archery, badminton, baseball, basketball, dance, fencing, field hockey, gymnastics, horseback riding, softball, swimming, tennis, track, volleyball, and waterskiing. Of special note are images of the first women's basketball team in 1898-1899. The collection also includes several images of dance performances and pageants.
All of the images are photographic prints and have been assigned individual numbers. Several images in the collection are available online. Many of the photographs were published in the Beaver yearbook.
Collection is open for research.
The collection consists of one series: I. Women's Athletic Teams and Events, 1899-1958.
The images were acquired by the Archives from various sources primarily during the 1960s.
Additional photographs of women's athletes and athletic teams and events are available in Harriet's Collection. The Women's Recreation Association (WRA) Photographic Collection (P 171) consists of images of athletic events and recreational activities, primarily during the 1950s-1960s; the Oregon State University Women's Basketball and Field Hockey Scrapbooks include photographs of teams and and events during the 1960s. The Betty Lynd Thompson Papers include extensive materials document dance instruction and performances at Oregon State; the Health and Human Performance Records (RG 031) include materials pertaining to physical education and recreational activities at Oregon State.
Oregon Agricultural College--Sports.; Oregon Agricultural College--Students.; Oregon State College--Sports.; Oregon State College--Students.
Basketball for women--Oregon--Corvallis.; College sports for women--Oregon--Corvallis.; College students--Oregon--Corvallis.; Dance--Study and teaching--Oregon--Corvallis.; Field hockey--Oregon--Corvallis.; Intramural sports--Oregon--Corvallis.; Modern dance.; Physical education for women--Oregon--Corvallis.; Student activities--Oregon--Corvallis.; Women--Education (Higher)--Oregon--Corvallis.; Women--Recreation--Oregon--Corvallis.
Photographic prints.
Colleges and Universities; Performing Arts; Sports and Recreation; Student Life; Women; Corvallis; Photographs
- Women's Athletic Teams and Events, 1899-1958; Series I
  Series I consists of photographs of individual athletes and teams as well as athletic events and recreational activities. The names of identified individuals are included in the description; images that were published in the Beaver yearbook are indicated as such.
  - Captain Alta Mentzer, circa 1920; P009:01; 2 prints (Box 1)
    Basketball player.
  - Junior hockey team, circa 1920; P009:03; 2 prints (Box 1)
  - Tennis action, circa 1920; P009:04; 2 prints (Box 1)
  - Softball scene, circa 1920; P009:05 (Box 1)
  - Women's basketball team, 1899; P009:07 (Box 1)
    Standing L-R: Inez Fuller, Coach Will Beach, Bessie Smith, Lona [Lana?] Smith. Sitting L-R: Leta Owensby, Fanny Getty
  - College basketball team, 1899; P009:08; 2 prints (Box 1)
    L-R: Bessie G. Smith, Letita Ownsbey, Elizabeth Hoover, Coach Will Beach, Minnie Smith, Inez Fuller (by banner in-front). Published in the June 1900 Souvenir Edition of the Barometer, which is available online.
  - Women athletes, circa 1904; P009:09; 2 prints (Box 1)
    Kneeling: Alice Wicklund, Eva Stoats (Mrs. FC Ritner), Edith Prince, Alice Jones, Maud Roberts (Mrs. HC Brodie), Margaret May Martin, Verna Kerker, Mary Elgin. Sitting: Ruth Lilly (Mrs. EH Pratt), Winnie Logan (Mrs. ER Woods), Maggie Maud Hays, Reta Price, Edna Buster (Mrs. JS Wheeler), Myrtle Harrington, Elizabeth "Bess" Yates, Mabel Stovall, Louise Gilbert. In Front: Reva Buell, Hazel Raber (Mrs. JC Ewing),Luella "Mary" VanCleve (Mrs. FL Stephens). Standing: Bess Danneman, Mary Danneman, Loene Montgomery, Laura Persinger, Alice Edwards, Lucile Roberts, Pearl Persinger, Candice Wicklund, Essie Adams, Jessie Wilson, Margaret McCormick, Gretta Harringtion, Una Stewart (Mrs. JW Carlson), Frances Gellatly, Madeline Nichols.
  - Women's gymnastic team in a gymnastic formation, circa 1930s; P009:10; 2 prints (Box 1)
  - Winning junior basketball team, 1929; P009:11 (Box 1)
    Pearl Horning, Alma Taylor, Mabel Harding, Eleanor Tonsing, Ruth Rydell, Martha Jane Pocklington, Audra Liska, Elda Aasen, Florence Kaufman.
  - Women in May Day pageant doing dance depiction of the history of Oregon, 1921; P009:12 (Box 1)
    Published in the 1921 Beaver yearbook, page 310.
  - Women fencing in gym class, 1938; P009:13 (Box 1)
    Published in the 1938 Beaver yearbook, page 216.
  - Three women pinning one to the ground in fencing class, 1938; P009:14 (Box 1)
  - Three women playing basketball in gym class, 1938; P009:15 (Box 1)
    Published in the 1938 Beaver yearbook, page 214.
  - Two women playing badminton in gym class, 1938; P009:16 (Box 1)
    Published in the 1938 Beaver yearbook, page 215.
  - The physical education club on the steps of the Women's Building, 1940; P009:17 (Box 1)
    Published in the 1940 Beaver yearbook, page 149.
  - Badminton in the Women's Building, played by two women, 1940; P009:18 (Box 1)
    Published in the 1940 Beaver yearbook, page 147.
  - Members of the Archery Club sitting around a target outside the Women's Building, 1940-1941; P009:19 (Box 1)
    Published in the 1940 Beaver yearbook, page 148.
  - Women playing volleyball in the Women's Building, 1938; P009:20 (Box 1)
  - Women in modern dance class, 1938; P009:21 (Box 1)
  - Women playing baseball in field behind Women's Building, 1938; P009:22 (Box 1)
  - Women swimming in pool, probably playing some kind of water polo, 1938; P009:23 (Box 1)
    Published in the 1938 Beaver yearbook, page 218.
  - Women playing basketball in Women's Building, 1940; P009:24 (Box 1)
    Published in the 1940 Beaver yearbook, page 146.
  - Women playing volleyball in gym class, in the Women's Building, 1940; P009:25 (Box 1)
  - Captain and member of the junior basketball team, 1921; P009:26 (Box 1)
  - Junior volleyball champions, 1929; P009:27 (Box 1)
    Includes Frances Reid, Captain, Commerce; Helen Wirkkala, Commerce; Marie Baumback, Home Economics; June Hudson, Commerce; Gennette Miner, Home Economics; and Lan Chen Kung, Home Economics. Published in 1929 Beaver yearbook, page 245.
  - Women's swimming group, 1941; P009:28 (Box 1)
    Includes Audrey Louise Johnson.
  - Sharon Spencer, Homecoming Queen for 1958-1959, waterskiing at the Cypress Gardens in Florida, P009:29; 2 prints (Box 1)
  - Double badminton championship for Sackett B, 1951; P009:30 (Box 1)
    Marjorie English and Virginia Moses.
  - Orchesis members in a dance formation, 1951; P009:31 (Box 1)
    Pat Kelley and Phyllis Horseman.
  - Track, a girl jumping over the high jump, circa 1925; P009:32; 2 prints (Box 1)
  - Track, woman preparing to throw discus jump, circa 1925; P009:33 (Box 1)
  - Baseball team playing in field behind Women's Building; Weatherford Hall in background., 1940; P009:34 (Box 1)
    Published in 1940 Beaver yearbook, page 148.
  - Volleyball game in the Women's gym, 1938; P009:35 (Box 1)
    Published in 1938 Beaver yearbook, page 215.
  - Track; four women running the hurdles in front of the stadium, circa 1925; P009:36 (Box 1)
  - Track; a woman jumping the high jump, circa 1925; P009:37 (Box 1)
  - Woman jumping the broad jump on track behind bleachers, circa 1925; P009:38 (Box 1)
  - Junior basketball team, 1921; P009:39 (Box 1)
    Published in the 1921 Beaver yearbook, page 305.
  - Physical education dance group outside on the lawn, circa 1930; P009:40 (Box 1)
  - Dance pageant on the lawn, 1923; P009:41; 3 prints and 2 oversize prints (Box 1-2)
    Published in the 1923 Beaver yearbook, page 319.
  - Mother's Day pageant, women dancing on the lawn, 1925; P009:42 (Box 1)
  - Mother's Day pageant, women dancing on the lawn, 1925; P009:43; 3 prints (Box 1)
  - Women's field hockey, P009:44 (Box 1)
  - Two women in dance or formal dresses, circa 1925; P009:45 (Box 1)
  - Four women with horses, circa 1930; P009:46 - P009:47 (Box 1)
    Equestrian team (?).